Hey everyone, so it’s been almost exactly
a year since I published my innocuous little
flat earth debunk as part of my astronomy series.
That was the one that the globebusters foolishly
engaged with, and their idiotic insult-filled
commentary prompted me to make this little
gem that they never recovered from.
Then based on the ridiculous comments I received
on that video, I made one more to mock the
moronic things that all flat earthers say
verbatim, or at least they did until that
video made the rounds.
And then I put the whole thing down for a while.
It was never my intention to make that sort
of content, but it was quite satisfying, and
I got ten times the views of my normal content,
which was definitely a plus.
But I had to move on,
lest I be tempted to rebrand myself from a
channel with academic intentions to one devoted
purely to debunking con men.
However, it’s been a year, I’ve done so
many tutorials since then, so why not jump
back in the muck for a moment.
This time, I’d like to offer some challenges
to you remaining few that are desperately
clinging to this dying fad to derive some
semblance of self-worth.
Let’s call them:
Ten Challenges for Flat Earthers.
These will be some basic things that anyone
could do to test the flat earth hypothesis.
They are so mind-numbingly obvious, that the
fact that you don’t do them is an immediate
indicator of your complete lack of intellectual
integrity.
Let’s get started and you’ll see what
I mean.
Number one.
Here’s the flat earth map that you all seem
to agree upon.
Anyone with half a brain can immediately tell
that this does not correlate with reality,
but for those with an even smaller fraction,
let’s do a few things to prove it.
For example, make a scale.
You know, a scale?
It’s that thing on maps that tells you how
far away things are from each other.
Look at this map.
There’s a scale.
You can pick two cities and determine the
approximate distance between them.
Then you can drive your car from one to another
and verify that it is the correct distance.
Now back to your little map.
Where’s the scale here?
Why do you never include one?
Is it because it’s impossible?
Yes, that is exactly why.
And if you disagree, here’s your challenge.
Pick some distance on this map.
A centimeter, an inch, whatever.
Tell me the distance it corresponds to in reality.
Then, pick some cities, and use your scale
to estimate the distances between them.
Pick two on the same continent, pick two on
different continents.
Use it to tell me how wide this inappropriately
enormous ocean is.
Use it to tell me literally anything about
the distances between literally anything.
When you can’t do it, and your numbers do
not correlate with reality in the slightest,
recall that this map does it just fine, and
then admit that your map is stupid.
Your complete inability to make any kind of
remotely legitimate map single-handedly proves
the earth isn’t flat.
But let’s continue just for fun.
Number two.
As we all know, the existence of Antarctica
poses a huge problem for you.
When it is summer in the northern hemisphere,
you love to pretend that the sun moves inwards
to this tropic, making the days longer here,
and shorter in the southern hemisphere.
And then when it’s winter in the north,
you like to put the sun at the other tropic,
which you think gives you the shorter days
up north that you want, but in the south it’s
total chaos.
You have the sun tracing this enormous trajectory,
which would leave everything out here in darkness
for most of the day, when in reality, there
are long periods of time in Antarctica where
the sun never sets.
Since your dinky little sun can never illuminate
this entire fantasy ice wall at once, this
compeletely obliterates your model, which
is why you resort to conspiracy.
You simply deny that this midnight sun ever
occurs, while claiming that no one can go
to Antarctica to verify it for themselves,
because the government NASA Jew penguins will
kill you.
Well apart from all the commercial cruises,
civilians can even apply for jobs there, so
you totally could go see it for yourself.
But you don’t really have to go all the
way to Antarctica.
Just go to the tip of South America, like
this town where people live.
Or don’t even go there, just look up times
of sunrise and sunset on the internet.
In mid-December, sunrise is earlier than 5
AM, and sunset is later than 10 PM.
Now take your little model for the seasons,
and make it show night and day.
Then try and make the night and day portions
match up with these sunrise and sunset times.
Demonstrate the light from the sun illuminating
this location for more than 70 percent of
its trajectory.
And as you do that, make sure that it does
not illuminate Point Barrow, Alaksa, whatsoever
during its entire trajectory, as that town
has endless night during this time of the year.
That’s right.
Lots of sun over here, and zero sun over here.
Good luck.
If you decide to even try, observe that the
light patterns become so nonsensical that
not even the most meth-fueled creatives amongst
you could vomit enough magnetism jargon to
justify it.
If you can’t make your model show the seasons
and night and day at the same time, as I pointed
out that you can’t almost a year ago, then
seriously consider shutting up forever.
Number three.
Here’s an idea.
What if you were to actually make a prediction
with your model?
Like, any prediction.
You know, those things you have to do in science
for it to be science?
Pick any celestial object.
A planet.
A comet.
A star.
Now pick any time in the future.
And using only the flat earth model and nothing
else, tell me where it will be at that time.
If you can’t do this, and I know you can’t,
consider admitting that your model is absolutely
irrelevant.
People who actually understand the geometry
of the earth and the solar system can predict
a solar eclipse, specifying the start and
end time down to the second, and tracing its
precise path down to the square mile.
Doing that even a single time means the model
used to make the prediction has been undeniably
verified, and it’s done every single time.
Anyone who doesn’t see the importance of
that has no clue how science works.
Number four.
After I demolished essentially all of your
favorite talking points in my previous videos,
you all now cling primarily to the classic
“I shouldn’t see this thing” argument.
You love this one because you can lie about
heights and distances, do incorrect math,
and in general act incredulous without having
to actually do any science.
Well every time you whine about this, the
objects are always suspiciously close, such
that you can fudge the numbers, and they’re
always over water, so you can lie about refractive
effects to people who have no idea how refraction
works.
So try this one on for size.
Show me a picture of something over land that’s
a thousand miles away.
May I suggest the middle of the country where
there’s not much in the way.
It’s a straight shot after all, so what’s
the problem?
Use a telescope.
Pull Las Vegas into focus from Dallas, Texas.
Isn’t that where you have your little meeting?
Maybe you should try doing something productive
rather than blindly perpetuating the dumbest
hoax on the internet.
Number five.
Speaking of things that are far away, you
all love whipping out your Nikons so much
that I wouldn’t be surprised if a Nikon
executive dreamt up the entire flat earth
hoax as a viral marketing campaign.
You take a boat that’s far away, pull it
back into focus, and then marvel at your own
brilliance for figuring out how to operate
a camera.
Well try this one then.
Stay on the boat.
Don’t cut away.
Stay on it until it disappears.
How will it disappear?
Bottom up.
Just like everything else.
I wonder why you’ve never put that on YouTube?
Number six.
The most hilarious thing about flat earth
is that the most mundane, every day observations
make absolutely no sense in your model.
Like a sunset.
A small sun above a flat earth would simply
recede high in the sky and get smaller and
smaller until it fades away.
It absolutely would not retain the same angular
size and set below the horizon.
It stays the same size because it’s unbelievably
far away, and it sets below the horizon because
the earth is a sphere that is turning.
Even a toddler can understand this.
It’s so blatantly obvious that you have
to resort to your typical ad hoc antics, talking
about refractive effects that defy all logic
and somehow magically apply to the sun but
nothing else.
Or even better, some of you talk about about
a dome with the sun on the other side that
produces some bizarre optical effect.
Apart from the sheer absurdity of this magical
dome that no one has ever seen or touched,
it creates big problems for you, because you
also claim that the sun and moon perform other
kinds of magic to push the air and water around,
to get tides and storms and what have you.
That would require that it is inside the dome.
So which is it?
Is the sun outside of the magical non-existent
dome, so you can pretend to get the sunset,
or is it inside the magical non-existent dome,
so you can pretend to get the tides?
It can’t be both.
Or if you bail on the dome and say it’s
just water, how do all those water molecules
that make up around one percent of the atmosphere
produce a thousand times greater refractive
effect than actual liquid water?
How does the appearance of a sunset never
vary at all, whether it’s dry or humid or raining?
Why does nothing else but the sun behave that way?
Show me a projectile or a plane going below
the horizon as it recedes.
Or show me this dome and explain the phenomena
with more than buzzwords.
Do something to explain a sunset.
Do anything besides making idiotic videos
with action movie soundtracks that contradict
middle school level science.
Number seven.
What the hell is a lunar eclipse to you?
Seriously.
Explain anything about a lunar eclipse.
The things you say about solar eclipses are
stupid enough, but at least you say something.
A lunar eclipse happens when the earth gets
between the sun and the moon.
That’s right.
In between.
These two objects are not perpetually above
a flat plane, and you know it, which is why
you’re totally silent on lunar eclipses.
And if you’re going to propose that some
other object besides the earth is what obscures
the moon, good luck trying to demonstrate
its existence.
Number eight.
Speaking of the sun and moon being small and
close to the earth, what is stopping you from
strapping a camera to a weather balloon and
sending it up there?
Go get up close and personal with either of
these objects and take some pictures.
If you get crafty with some robotics, which
is a stretch given your complete lack of education,
you could even scoop up a little sample.
Maybe the moon is made of cheese after all.
Can’t you get even halfway there, such that
the sizes change?
Reach for the sky, fellas.
Number nine.
Take some flights.
Like any direct flight in the southern hemisphere.
Whoops!
Shouldn’t that be impossible?
Better yet, fly between two cities two different
ways, the shortest way on the globe, and the
shortest way on the flat earth.
Which one do you think will be faster?
I’m just joking, I know that none of you
will ever be employed long enough to afford
a private jet.
But next time you’re on a regular plane,
notice that flights going east or west are
not constantly turning slightly to one side,
as you seem to believe they all must be.
Yeah.
You would notice that.
If humanity is unfortunate enough that you’ve
actually procreated, send your kid up to the
cockpit to meet the pilot and snap a pic of
the wheel.
What do you know, straight as an arrow.
And number ten.
Do anything legitimately scientific, at all.
Publish anything whatsoever about your model
in anything reputable anywhere.
Invent any technology based on your model.
Do anything at all that could be considered
actual empirical science.
Here’s a hint, you may have to study some
real science to do it, but then of course
you would immediately learn that the earth
isn’t flat, so it probably won’t be of
much use.
So that’s it for the ten challenges.
I say the word challenge facetiously, since
all of you will immediately recognize the
futility, and resort instead to calling me
names in the comments section.
You flat earth priests with your waste of
space channels know full well that doing anything
even remotely empirical demolishes your hoax,
which is why you stick to shouting conspiracy,
and very little else.
And you handful of mindless followers hanging
on to the only thing that makes you feel special,
maybe 2020 is the year you finally get a clue
and move on with your lives.
There’s a whole spherical world out there,
a world filled with people who won’t instantly
mock you or be ashamed to know you.
There are so many opportunities to actually
be a person of even minor consequence.
I know I’ve been hard on you, but I really
am rooting for you folks.
All you have to do is disengage from these
charlatans that lie for a living.
Save that ten dollar superchat and buy yourself
some dignity, or even put it in a college
fund so you can go to school and learn something useful.
The choice is yours.
Good luck, and good night.