Hey everyone.
So there’s been a resurgence of interest
in my channel among flat earthers lately.
First, there’s this intellectual powerhouse...
who tried to debunk my ten things that all
flat earthers say by repeating the ten things
that all flat earthers say.
Great work, slick.
Then the globebusters, no doubt still upset
about my video that exposed their unparalleled
stupidity to millions of people, which continues
to get between ten and twenty thousand views
per day, are publishing feature length responses
made by some nitwit to my ten challenges,
which literally do not respond to the challenges.
I ask for a map, 90 minutes later, I kid you
not, no map.
So with the dwindling flat earth cult now
a pathetic parody of itself, I’m just going
to do a few more videos demonstrating how
easy it is to destroy flat earth without using
any science at all.
Last time we looked at the moon, so today,
let’s look at the stars.
Flat earthers love to complain about how dumb
it is to look up at the sky to determine the
shape of the earth, but that’s only because
doing so specifically proves that it’s a
sphere, and it’s one of the ways we figured
out that it’s a sphere thousands of years ago.
For example, if you’re at a northernly latitude
facing northwards and you watch the stars
for a while, you will notice that they appear
to rotate counterclockwise around a point
in the sky.
This point is roughly aligned with the star
Polaris, which we call the north star.
If you were to then travel south for a while,
you would see that certain stars are no longer
viewable, and at the equator, all the stars
move directly east to west through the sky.
Then, heading towards the southernly latitudes
and facing south, you will see a whole new
batch of stars you couldn’t see in the north,
and they will again be rotating around a point
in the sky, though this time clockwise instead
of counterclockwise.
So, how do we make sense of these observations?
Do they work on a flat earth?
Not even a little bit.
That the sky would be doing different things
for different people just because they are
standing closer or further from the center
of a disk is total nonsense.
That’s why flat earthers avoid this subject
all together, unless they have the balls to
invent idiotic sorcery like personal domes
and other fantasies that are not even worth
deconstructing.
Furthermore, why can’t people towards the
outer edge see the same stars as people towards
the center?
And vice versa?
What’s blocking the light?
Again, no explanation.
Now what would happen on a sphere that is
turning?
Standing up north, whichever point in the
sky is aligned with the rotational axis would
appear not to move, and everything else would
rotate around it.
Just like we see.
Standing in the south, same thing, but the
opposite direction from their perspective.
Also, any star that would require a line of
sight that cuts through the earth is not visible,
because we can’t see through the earth.
That’s why southerners can’t see Polaris,
and northerners can’t see the Southern Cross.
But that’s not all, literally all observations
of the sky from the southern hemisphere are
utterly inexplicable on the flat earth.
Consider people standing towards the southern
tips of South America, Africa, and Australia.
They all can see the Southern Cross when they
look south, and two of them at a time can
even see it simultaneously, depending on the
time of night.
Does that make any sense with these folks
all looking in completely different directions?
None whatsoever.
Come to think of it, what does “south”
even mean on a flat earth?
It’s totally nonsensical.
But again, on a sphere, south actually means
something, and all these people are looking
in the same direction, towards the south celestial pole.
So they can all see the same sky, no problem.
Now, most flat earthers have heard all of
this before, and instead of admitting to themselves
that the logic is airtight, they just ignore
all of it, and bring up unrelated objectively
incorrect talking points.
At least a thousand times I’ve been asked
why the stars don’t change throughout the
year if we are orbiting the sun.
Well, they do.
The stars that lie near the ecliptic are obscured
half the year, because they are on the other
side of the sun, and we can’t see stars
during the daytime because of how bright the sun is.
These are the zodiac constellations, the ones
from astrology, so it’s shocking that you’re
not familiar with them, since you’re so
in love with pseudoscience.
The stars that can be viewed in a direction
closer to perpendicular to the ecliptic are
seen throughout the year, and there’s no
logical basis for thinking that they wouldn’t be.
They’re really far away.
Earth’s orbital radius is negligible in comparison.
But because of earth’s orbit, they do shift
their positions slightly throughout the year.
It’s called stellar parallax.
I would link to my tutorial that explains
what that is, but I know learning is not really
your thing.
Eh, here it is anyway.
Give it a look if you’re feeling bold.
So that’s it.
Once again, looking at the sky with your eyeballs
is all you need to do to demonstrate that
the earth is a sphere.
And once again, that’s how the ancients
figured out that the earth is a sphere, without
having a clue about literally anything else.
They thought astrology was true, and that
demons are real, and yet, they got this one down.
If you can’t manage that, you’re allergic
to thinking, and there’s no point in talking to you.
To everyone else, see you next time.